Francis Davis Millet Collection
Francis Davis Millet Collection
1876-1981
0.25 linear ft.
Biographical material, correspondence about, and photographs of paintings by, the American painter, sculptor and writer. No original Millet material.
2725730
Biographical History
Francis Davis Millet (1846-1912) was an American painter, sculptor, and writer. He served as a drummer boy during the Civil War, graduated from Harvard, and worked as a reporter and editor for the Boston Courier and as a war correspondent for several British and American newspapers. His painting took him from Rome, where he had a studio for several years and lived with travel journalist Charles Warren Stoddard, to Venice and later back to the United States; among his close friends were painter John Singer Sargent, author Mark Twain and sculptor Augustus Saint-Gaudens. Millet was a member of the American Academy of Arts and Letters and an honorary member of the American Institute of Architects. He died in the sinking of the Titanic on April 15, 1912.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Francis Davis Millet Collection consists of research material relating to Millet. The material appears to have been collected by Thomas B. Brumbaugh, professor of fine art at Vanderbilt University. Material includes correspondence between Brumbaugh and various repositoties requesting photographs of paintings by Millet, as well as correspondence between Brumbaugh and various relatives of Millet's. Other material includes photocopies of articles and clippings about Millet, Stoddard, and Twain; research notes; correspondence with dealers about Millet and Stoddard letters; and miscellaneous related items. A good portion of the material concerns Millet's relationship with Charles Warren Stoddard and his friendship with Mark Twain.
The collection contains no original material from Millet, Stoddard, or Twain, only secondary material about them.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
The library has several books by Millet, both in the circulating collections and in our rare books holdings. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Brumbaugh, Thomas B. (Thomas Brendle), 1921-2011.; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912.; Stoddard, Charles Warren, 1843-1909.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.; Journalists -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Research notes.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - American Federation of Arts, 1922; "Francis Davis Millet Memorial Meeting" program, 63 pp. (Box 1)
  - Clippings about, 1876-1977; photocopies only, no originals (Box 1)
  - MIllet family, 1973; corespondence with Millet relatives (Box 1)
  - Paintings by, clippings, photographs, other reproductions (Box 1)
  - Reproduction requests, 1973-1974; 1981 (Box 1)
  - Research notes, index cards with names of people, paintings (Box 1)
  - Stoddard, Charles W., 1974; 1978,; undated; includes a typed manuscript (Box 1)
  - Twain, Mark, 1950-1951; 1967,; 1972,; 1974,; 1976,; undated; includes original copies of The Twainian newsletter (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1973-1974; 1976,; 1978; several from manuscripts dealers (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, includes photo of bas-relief of Millet by Saint-Gaudens (Box 1)